Guide to the Alice L. Hageman Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Alice L. Hageman Papers
1957-2014
RG 272
Yale University Divinity School Library
5.5
14 boxes
Correspondence, writings, pamphlets, notes, and other records document the activities of Alice Hageman, a social activist, attorney, and Presbyterian minister.
Hageman, Alice L.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alice L. Hageman, 2016
Scope and Contents
This collection documents Hageman's lifelong involvement in social justice and ecumenical work, including her participation in international ministry through Frontier Internship in Mission, her founding of the Committee of Returned Volunteers and the Cuba Resource Center during the Cold War, her extensive involvement with the World Student Christian Federation. Her work and personal life are closely intertwined with other ecumenical women of the era, including Margaret Flory, for whom she organized a number of events. The collection provides valuable primary source documentation of the activities of the Committee of Returned Volunteers and other organizations during the late 1960s and early 1970s, including protests against the Vietnam war, U.S. engagement in Latin America, and other social justice issues. A complementary collection of Alice L. Hageman papers is held by the Wisconsin Historical Society.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Series I. Writings
Series II. Sermons / Talks / Worship Materials
Series III. Educational and Legal Work
Series IV. Organizations Served
Series V. Personal and Collected Material
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Chronology of Alice L. Hageman
1937 June 12 Alice Hageman born to Lillian Mac Little Hageman and Maurice Herman Hageman in Hightstown, New Jersey
1954-1958 Attended College of Wooster. Spent a semester in Washington, D.C.
1958 After graduation from college, spent summer traveling Europe and participated in a month-long World Council of Churches (WCC) work camp in Battersea, London, beginning her ecumenical career
1958 Enrolled in Union Theological Seminary's Master of Religious Education program (Manhattan, NY). Did field education in East Harlem Protestant Parish
1959-1960 With Presbyterian Work and Study fellowship spent a year in Geneva gaining exposure to the world church. Studied at the University of Geneva (Geneva, Switzerland) and the Ecumenical Institute (Bossey, Switzerland.)
1959 December Ecumenical Student Conference on Christian World Mission took place in Athens, Ohio, planting the seed of the Frontier Internship in Mission (FIM) program
1960 CIMADE (Comite Intermouvement Aupres Des Evacues) Internships in Coudekerque and Marseilles, France
1960 June First FIM intern appointed.
1960 July: Helped organize the World Student Christian Federation's (WSCF) international teaching conference on the Life and Mission of the Church and attended as a steward. (Strasbourg, France) September: returned to Union Theological Seminary, this time as a Bachelor of Divinity student.
1961 First FIM class of interns appointed.
1962 Graduated with B.D. (M.Div) from Union Theological Seminary
1962-1965 Participated in Frontier Internship in Mission program orchestrated by Margaret Flory and assigned the frontier of the "emerging international community" Served as WSCF representative at UNESCO (Paris, France)
1963 January Attended WSCF meeting in Brighton, England with Milan Opocensky
1963 summer Attended a consultation in Geneva between International Union of Students and WSCF, a rare exchange of ideas between Western Europe and those behind the Iron Curtain. Met future friends and colleagues from Cuba
1964 July Attended Christian Peace Conference as WSCF representative. Met future Cuban contacts. (Prague, Czech Republic)
1965 Returned to U.S.
1966 Moved back to Manhattan and began project under the auspices of the Ecumenical Foundation for Higher Education in Metropolitan New York. Began working with Aubrey Brown to organize former/returned Peace Corps volunteers to make known their experiences in third-world countries and to protest the Vietnam War
1966 December Committee of Returned Volunteers (CRV) convened formally for the first time and chose its name. As part of CRV, Alice participated in protests, rallies, and demonstrations, and helped write position papers on Southeast Asia and Latin America.
1967 CRV published position paper on Vietnam, sparking development of other CRV chapters around the country.
1968 Spring Participated with CRV graduate student members in protest/"occupation" at Columbia University.
1968 August Attended the Democratic Convention as a demonstrator/protester and was tear-gassed by police. (Chicago, IL)
1969 June Together with three colleagues, terminated from their campus ministry positions with the Ecumenical Foundation for outspokenness against the Vietnam War. As a CRV delegate, Hageman used her remaining EF travel budget to travel to Cuba, despite the absence of diplomatic relations between Cuba and the U.S. In Cuba, she toured the island, tended banana plants, and worked at a coffee plantation. She cultivated an interest in gender issues. She returned to the U.S. on a fishmeal/sugar freighter bound for Canada.
1969-1971 Co-founded and served as a director of the Cuba Resource Center (CRC) to facilitate the exchange of resources between U.S. and Cuba. As CRC staff, she produced publications, started a newsletter, and organized three ecumenical trips to Cuba.. Edited book (Religion in Cuba Today: New Church in a New Society.)
1970 Helped secure Campaigns for United Ministries in Higher Education funds for a campus ministry women's caucus (forerunner of the WSCF Women's Project in North America).
1971 Moved to Boston, MA for a one-year Danforth campus ministries grant. (Jamaica Plain, Boston)
1972 Lentz Lecturer on women and ministry, Harvard Divinity School. Edited book (Sexist Religion and Women in the Church).
1972-1986 Participated in team ministry at Church of the Covenant. (Back Bay, Boston, MA)
1974-1977 Attended Northeastern University Law School.
1975 Ordained as Presbyterian minister.
1977-1989 Graduated with a J.D. from Northeastern University Law School. Joined a community law practice and practiced law for 12 years
1979 CRC ceased operations
1980 Filed a Freedom of Information Act request and received a heavily redacted FBI file documenting her activities since her time in Cuba
1989-2001 Served as assistant bar counsel of the Board of Bar Overseers of the Supreme Judicial Court of Massachusetts prosecuting lawyers for professional misconduct.
2005 Married CRV colleague Aubrey N. Brown III (who died in 2015.)
2016 As of 2016 was serving as a U.S. Trustee of WSCF responsible for follow-up with Senior Friends and fundraising in the organization's second century.
Church work with students; Hageman, Alice L.; World Student Christian Federation; Committee of Returned Volunteers; Frontier Internship in Mission Programme; Hageman, Alice L.
- Writings, Series I
  - "Youth Education for International Understanding"; "A Death in the Family", 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Draft and paper written by Alice Hageman and presented at the Meeting of the World Christian Youth Commission in 1963 on Christian youth education in the international context.
  - "The WSCF and UNESCO"; "International Life and the Identity Crisis"; "The WSCF Political Commission and International Organizations", 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Some 'Problem Areas' in Literacy"; "In Search of News Words or an Authentic Silence:Christian Presence in the International Milieu", 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Some Reflections on Style of Life in the UCM", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Drafts and correspondence related to a paper written by Alice Hageman regarding "style of life" in the university Christian movement, presented at the NSCF Political Commission Meeting in 1966
  - "Internationalization of the University in Metropolitan New York", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Project proposal and report written under the auspices of the Ecumenical Foundation for Higher Education in Metropolitan New York.
  - "International Hypocrisy and the CIA" (in Wind and Chaff ); "The University, The Church and Internationalization" (co-authored by Margaret Flory), 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Role of Trade Unions in the Process of Soviet Development", 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Paper written by Alice Hageman for the university class Economics 1201 focusing on Soviet development in the early 20th century.
  - "The Courtroom as Sanctuary in American Civil Religion: An Anachronistic Expression of Anti-Democratic Mystification", 1977 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Report on judicial internship.
  - Commencement Speech, 1977 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Commencement speech given at Northeastern University Law School.
  - "Receiving Power"; "The Promise of Power", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Correspondence and drafts of two related manuscripts based on a Union Theological Seminary lecture and its corresponding sermon, both focusing on issues of power in the church with respect to women and the legal profession.
  - "Practicing Our Hope", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Drafts and final forms of Practicing Our Hope, and its abridged version Sustaining Our Hope, two papers written by Alice Hageman reflecting on the realities and challenges of doing community ecumenical work.
  - "Reflection on the Student Christian Movement of the 1960s and Its Effects on My Life" (in Journal of Ecumenical Studies ), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Statement of Faith; "Protestant Colonialism in the Spanish Caribbean", No date (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Sermons/Talks/Worship Materials, Series II
  - Sermons and sermon notes of AH, 1986, no date (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Hymns, prayers, notes, programs, correspondence, and other materials related to sermons, services, and worship-based events planned, attended, or spoken at by Alice Hageman
  - Liturgies, hymns, prayers, 2008-2009, no date (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Educational and Legal Work, Series III
  - Education / training
    - College of Wooster, 1954-1958 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Union Theological Seminary, 1958-1962, 1978, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Cours de Civilisation Francaise a la Sorbonne, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Harvard University, special student program; funded by Danforth Campus Ministry Grant, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Includes documentation regarding other applications and references.
    - Ordination in Presbyterian Church U.S.A., 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    - Northeastern University School of Law, 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 7-10)
      First folder contains applications to and correspondence with other law schools.
  - Legal positions
    - Job applications / correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Academic institutions
    - Harvard Divinity School: denominational counselor for Presbyterian students / polity courses taught, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - Application for position at McCormick Theological Seminary, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Application for position at Mt. Holyoke College, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Organizations Served, Series IV
  - Frontier Internship in Mission / Bi-National Service
    - Correspondence and documents, 1959 April - 1963 March (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Including: "Cooperation Between the World Council of Churches and UNESCO"; "Some Reflections on the Role of the Commission on its Overseas Responsibilities"; "A Plan for Study and Service on Strategic Frontiers in the Christian Mission"
    - Correspondence and documents, 1963 March - September (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Includes, among others: "Some Evaluations, Generalizations, and Convictions" by David and Marylee Wiley;; "Finding the Freedom to be Human" by Harry Morton; "Suggestions for a Possible Colloquium on the "Christian Presence" in International Organizations"
    - Correspondence of Alice Hageman; reflections by Frontier Interns; "Frontier Study and Service at UNESCO: A Report" by Alice Hageman, 1963 October -1964 June (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Reports, 1964 June - August (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Including: "Frontier Study and Service at UNESCO: A Report" by Alice Hageman; "The Christian Community in the Academic World" by the General Committee of the World Student Christian Federation; "Frontier Internship in Mission: UNESCO—August, 1964" by Alice Hageman
    - Writings and notes, 1964 December - 1965 March (Box 4, Folder 5)
      "Case Studies in Lay Mission"; written notes by Alice Hageman; "Christian Vocation in International Civil Service" and "Suggestions" for that document; "Le Fonctionnaire International Et Le Monde D'Aujourd'Hui"
    - Reports and presentation, 1965 May - August (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Including: "The Christian Vocation in International Civil Service" presentation notes and answers to questions; "Christian Peace Conference Youth Commission, Hochst, 14-19th June 1965" documents; "Report: Frontier Internship Evaluation Conference, Princeton, New Jersey, August 14-18, 1965"
    - "Minutes of a Meeting of the Executive Committee of the WSCF, Cambridge, USA, 1965 August (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence to/from Valdo Galland, General Secretary of WSCF and Rev. Paul Frelick; responses to "Organisations internationals et le developpement", 1965 August - 1966 June (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Reflection, proposal, minutes, 1966 August - December (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Including: "Reflections on the Historical Context and the Political Stance of the University Christian Movement" by Dave Robinson; "Proposal for a Frontier Study and Service Project Related to the International Dimension of the University in Metropolitan New York"; "Minutes of Political Committee Meeting, New York City, December 4, 1966"
    - Schedule for Frontier Intern orientation; "Communique: World Student Christian Federation Committee on Work among Foreign Students, No. 2", 1966 December - 1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Christian Peace Conference documents, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Including: "The University Christian Movement Ends"; "1960-1970 documents of the Youth Commission of the Christian Peace Conference; Christian Peace Conference documents from the "middle generation" gathering in Toronto in 1970
    - Reports, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Includes: "The Frontier Internship Program: An Overview After Ten Years" by Margaret Flory; "Frontier Internship in Mission: Evaluation After Ten Years 1961-71: a condensation"; "Internationalization of the Frontier Internship Program"
    - Mailing list, reports, 1973 April - 1975 December (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Including: "The Frontier Intern Mailing List as of April 1, 1973"; "Center for Constitutional Rights Docket Report 1974"; "Report: International Working Party on the Internationalization of the Frontier Internship Program, Gwatt, Switzerland, July 1 to 6, 1974"; "Center for Constitutional Rights Report 1974-1975"
    - "10 Years: Bi-National Service"; Bi-National Service annual reports, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Bi-National Service annual reports; "The Exodus: East Bay Sanctuary Coalition Newsletter, Vol. 1 No. 1, August, 1982"; letters from Church World Service, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - "Frontier Internship in Mission Newsletter, 1983 Summer"; correspondence from The Great Peace Journey, 1982-1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Bi-National Service Annual Reflections/Reports; Servants' Roster; directories, 1985, no date (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Bi-National Service: Occasional Newsletter, October 1985"; Week of Work agenda; "Links of BNS—Occasional Bulletin of the Bi-National Service, Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A., September, 1987", 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Blueprints: A Journal of Frontier Interns in Mission, October 1987, Issue #1 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Blueprints: A Journal of Frontier Interns in Mission, April 1988, Issue #2 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Bi-National Service: Week of Work, July 16-21, 1988; reports, contact list, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Including: roster of active members of Bi-National Servants as of January 1991; "A FIM History" paper draft, 1991-1993 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Frontier Internship in Mission Directory, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Frontier Internship in Mission Report 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Frontier Internship in Mission Directory, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Frontier Internship in Mission Directory, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Reports, programme, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Includes: BiNational Service Report on the Week of Work at the Chateau de Bossey Ecumenical Institute, January 6-13, 1999; "National and Ethnic Identities and the Unity of the Church"; "Frontier Internship in Mission 2000 Programme and Operational Prospectus and Financial Audit for 1998"
    - Bi-National Servants Annual Reports, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Frontier Internship in Mission 2001 Programme and Operational Prospectus and Financial Audit for 1999, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Including: "Frontier Internship in Mission Funding Strategy"; "A Brief Guide & Tips for Your Trip to Cuba, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Frontier Internship in Mission Directory, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Reports, programme, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Including: "Challenges for Frontier Internship in Mission" by Manuel Quintero; "Frontier Internship in Mission 2002 Programme and Operational Prospectus and Financial Audit for 2000"; "Quest for a Just World Order—The Struggle Must Continue" by Clement John
    - Frontier Internship in Mission International Coordinating Committee Meeting & 40th Anniversary Celebration Workbook Part One: Havana, Cuba, March 31-April 7, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
    - Reports, anniversary documentation, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
      Including: "Frontier Internship in Mission Staff Report: From Amman to Havana, October 1997 to April 2001"; worship texts and notes from 40th Anniversary Frontier Internship in Mission, Havana, Cuba
    - Frontier Internship in Mission handbook; includes printed emails to Alice Hageman, John Moyer, notes, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Reports, emails, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Bi-National Service Worldwide Ministries Division Presbyterian Church (USA) Annual Reports and Messages from members of the BiNational Service community 2001: April 2002"; emails from John Moyer, Paul Frelick
    - Frontier Internship in Mission Directory, 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, documents, 2004-2008 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      Including regarding "Promise: An International Conference on the Ecumenical Movement in the 20th Century and now - in honour of Milan Opocensky" from Scottish Churches House; "Changing World Perspectives—3/21/08 draft"; Milan Opocensky: "It's your story that's being told"
    - Correspondence, notes, program information about "Promise" Conference; Stony Point lodging reservations, 2008-2010 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous FIM and Student Christian Movement documents, 2010, no date (Box 6, Folder 16)
      Including: Student Christian Movement—United States of America Bylaws; "The Work of Worship: A Guide to Interactive Ecumenical Worship for SCM Chapters" by C. Paul Grenier; evaluation, program information for "Overcoming Violence: Encountering the Past, Engaging the Present, Empowering the Future" Conference, October 8-11, 2010, Atlanta, GA
    - Margaret Flory Events: 1980 celebration of Flory's ministry, 1979-1980 (Box 11, Folder 6-8)
      Alice Hageman was a long time colleague and friend of Margaret Flory, a noted ecumenist, leader of student religious work, and mission executive in the Presbyterian Church (USA) from 1944-1980 who began and directed innovative missions programs including Junior Year Abroad, Frontier Internships in Mission,and Bi-National Service. Hageman was instrumental in preparing for two major events in tribute to Margaret Flory Margaret Flory's papers are found in YDSL Record Group 86.
    - Margaret Flory events: 2004 celebration of Flory's 90th birthday, 2003-2004 (Box 11, Folder 9-13)
  - World Student Christian Federation
    Additional WSCF documentation that was received with the Hageman papers has been placed in Record Groups 46B and 46C, the World Student Christian Federation Board of Trustees in the U.S. Archives and the World Student Christian Federation, Archives - Addendum.
    - Women's History Project
      - Project participants and documentation, 1996-1998 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, 1994-1999 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Agreement with Rutgers University Press, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Drafts and comments for Hageman's contribution, 1998-2001 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Drafts and comments for others' contributions, 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Photographs and clippings documenting Hageman's WSCF activities (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Search committees for WSCF candidates
      - Chairperson, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Vice Chairperson, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 8-9)
      - Treasurer, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Co-General Secretary, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Board of Trustees and Senior Friends
      Additional materials related to the WSCF that were received with the Hageman papers have been placed in YDSL Record Group 46B, World Student Christian Federation, North American Board of Trustees and Record Group 46C, World Student Christian Federation Records - Addendum.
      - Preparation for WSCF Centennial events, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - WSCF Centennial events, 1994 February - September (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - WSCF Centennial events and follow-up, 1994 October - November, no month (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - WSCF participants' history project, 1994-1995 (Box 12, Folder 8)
        For special issue of the Journal of Ecumenical Studies, Vol. 32, No. 3 (Summer, 1995). Includes drafts and contribution of Hageman to the volume.
      - Formation of Senior Friends group; meeting in Berlin and follow-up, 1995-1996 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Board of Trustees in the U.S.A. meetings and communications, 1995-1996 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - WSCF Senior Friends U.S.A. directory, 1996 (Box 12, Folder 11)
        Additional Senior Friends directories are available in Record Group 46C
      - Board of Trustees in the U.S.A. meetings and communications, 1997 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - Board of Trustees in the U.S.A. meetings, including regarding Centennial Fund, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 13)
      - Board of Trustees in the U.S.A. meetings, including regarding Centennial Fund, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 14)
      - Board of Trustees in the U.S.A. meetings and communications, 2000 (Box 12, Folder 15)
      - Board of Trustees in the U.S.A. meetings and communications, 2001 (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - Board of Trustees in the U.S.A. meetings and communications, 2002 (Box 12, Folder 17)
      - Board of Trustees in the U.S.A. meetings and communications, 2003 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Board of Trustees in the U.S.A. meetings and communications, 2004 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Board of Trustees meetings, including regarding Second Century Fund, 2005 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Regarding WSCF women's programmes, 2005 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Regarding WSCF North America Region and Council for Ecumenical Student Christian Ministry, 2005-2006 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Second Century Fund, 2006 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Second Century Fund, 2007 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Trustees and Senior Friends meetings and communications, 2006 - 2007 February (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Trustees and Senior Friends meetings and communications, 2007 February - December, no month (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - WSCF Europe Senior Friends meeting in Budapest, February 2008 (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Senior Friends gathering in Montreal, August 2008 - arrangements, 2007-2008 (Box 13, Folder 11)